Guide to the Homer Jackson Dana Catalog and Brochure Collection 1915-1950
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Homer Jackson Dana Catalog and Brochure Collection
1915-1950
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Cage 88
Dana, Homer J. (Homer Jackson), 1890-1970
1 Linear foot of shelf space 2 Boxes
This collection consists of ephemeral materials collected by WSU Professor Homer Jackson Dana.
Homer Jackson Dana attended the State College of Washington (now Washington State University) where he completed a bachelor's degree in electrical engineering in 1915 and a master's degree in 1917. He remained at WSU as an instructor, then returned as a student to complete a second master's degree in mechanical engineering. He continued his association with WSU, first as a consulting engineer, and later as a research engineer until his retirement in 1960. Although his post was as a research engineer, Dana occasionally taught classes, participated in the education of graduate students, and served as director of the Engineering Experiment Station.
Dana's interest in engineering led to a series of experimental projects, including researching the effect of heavy automobile traffic on roads and highways, solving refrigeration and heat transfer and storage problems, and designing the Mason City Project to measure the amount of electricity a community consumed. He was awarded patents for multiple devices, including an emotional stress meter (lie detector) and a prototype home freezer. Together with Hubert V. Carpenter, he founded one of the first educational radio stations in the United States in 1922. The radio station, located in Pullman, WA, was originally named KFAE, becoming KWSC in 1926, and KWSU in 1969.
This collection consists of ephemeral materials collected by Homer Jackson Dana. It includes brochures, pamphlets, and catalogs for Automobiles 1915-1950 (Series 1), Tractors 1915-1919 (Series 2), Engines 1915-1918 (Series 3), Parts and Equipment 1915-1922 (Series 4), Appliances, Electric Lighting, and Miscellaneous 1915-1921 (Series 5) which includes operating manuals, parts lists, and other materials documenting mechanical and electrical technology.
This collection is arranged in 5 series. Each series is arranged alphabetically by manufacturer or company name; in some cases, miscellaneous items are placed at the end of each series.
This collection is open and available for research use.
Homer Jackson Dana donated this collection to the Washington State University Libraries at an unknown date.
Homer Jackson Dana Papers, 1890-1970 (Cage 299)
A Historical Sketch Describing the Growth of the Generation and Use of Electricity in Pullman and the Inland Empire Typescrypt, 1958 February 11 (Cage 1817) (Cage 1817)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Dana, Homer J. (Homer Jackson), 1890-1970 -- Archives
Automobiles -- History -- Sources; Engines -- History -- Sources; Tractors -- History -- Sources
Technology
- Series 1: Automobiles, 1915-1950
  - Buick Motor Company
    - Buick Valve-in-head Motor Cars: six cylinder open and closed models. (catalog, 2 copies), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - What Buick Valve in Head Means. (pamphlet), circa 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Instruction Book, 1918 Six Cylinder Models. (pamphlet), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cadillac
    - Finishing Touches. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Why an Eight-cylinder Cadillac? (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cadillac Passenger Cars: Type 57. (catalog), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Cadillac for Nineteen Hundred and Fifty. (catalog), circa 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Case
    - Case Automobiles: Style Cars: Six Cylinder for 1918. (catalog), circa 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cole
    - The Cole Aero-Eight. (catalog), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dodge
    - Dodge Brothers Motor Cars. (catalog), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Franklin Automobile Company
    - Why the Franklin will start readily with low test gasoline on the coldest winter day. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Eliminating 177 Unnecessary Parts. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - A Fat Spark Anytime. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Is it the Tires or the Car? Heavy Tire Expense is Unnecessary. (pamphlet), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Franklin Sedan: The American Woman and the Franklin Sedan. (pamphlet), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Are Spare Tires your only Guarantee of Tire Security? (pamphlet), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Wick Oiling. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Power from Piston Rings: As Secured in the Franklin Car of Today. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Keeping Dust and Grit out of the Cylinders. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Franklin Sedan. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Franklin Car. (catalog), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Gasoline Economy-the Real Test of Motor Car Thrift. (pamphlet), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hupmobile
    - The Hupmobile Series-R: What it is, how it looks, what it does. (catalog), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hupmobile the Comfort Car. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Hupmobile Specifications: Motor and Chassis Improvements. (brochure), 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Oldsmobile
    - Oldsmobile Economy Truck. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Model Fortyfive-A Eight Cylinder Touring Car. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Model 37 Six Touring Car and Roadster. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rickenbacker Motor Company
    - Rickenbacker Six: A Car Worthy of its Name. (catalog), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Do You Know that-? (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Story of the Hat in the Ring. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Rickenbacker Six: A Car Worthy of its Name. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Rolls Royce
    - Containing some recent appreciations of the Rolls Royce. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - A Cost Keeping System for the Automobile. (pamphlet), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Seattle Hotel Penbrook and Apartments. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series 2: Tractors, 1915-1919
  - Advance-Rumley Thresher Co.
    - Rumley OilPull Tractor. (catalog), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Aultman-Taylor Machinery Company
    - Instructions for Operating and Maintaining Aultman-Taylor Gasoline-Kerosene Tractors. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bean Spray Pump Co.
    - The Bean TrackPull Tractor Catalog 32. (catalog), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Buda Company
    - Model "BTU" Four Cylinder Unit Power Plant with Removable Cylinder Head. (catalog), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Buffalo Pitts Company
    - The Buffalo Pitts 40-70 Kerosene Gas Tractor. (catalog), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bull Tractor Company
    - The Big Bull: A Real Kerosene Tractor. (catalog), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Case Threshing Machine Company
    - Case Tractor Manual: Instructions on Operation and Care of Case 10-18 Tractor. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Caterpillar Tractor
    - Correct Lubrication of the Caterpillar Tractor. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Caterpillar 45 Tractor 72 Inch Thread: Price List and Parts. (catalog), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Caterpillar 75: Price List and Parts. (catalog), 1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chase Motor Truck Company
    - The Chase 9-18 Farm Tractor. (catalog), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dayton-Dick Co.
    - Things you ought to know about Power Farming with the Leader Tractor: Leader Model B 12-18. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fageol Motors Company
    - Fageol Walking Tractor. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Frick Company
    - Frick Tractors, Traction and Portable Engines, Threshers, Saw Mills, Stationary Engines, and Steam Boilers. (catalog), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hart-Parr Company
    - Care and Operation Instructions: 35 Brake H. P. Tractor. (pamphlet), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - International Harvester Company of America
    - Farm Power. (pamphlet), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Instructions for Operating the International 15-30-H. P.: Kerosene Tractor (4-Cylinder). (pamphlet), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - John Lauson Mfg. Co.
    - Instructions for Operating The Lauson Kerosene Tractor. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - La Crosse Tractor Co.
    - La Crosse Happy Farmer Tractor Model "F": Instruction Book and Repair Price List. (catalog), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Moline Plow Company
    - How to Operate Moline Universal Tractor Model D: Four Cylinder Engine and all other Features Desired in the Ultimate Tractor. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Monarch Tractor Co.
    - Monarch Tractor Performance. (pamphlet), circa 1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Repair List and Instruction Book for Starting and Operating the "Neverslip" and "Lightfoot" Gasoline and Oil Tractors. (pamphlet), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Lightfoot and Neverslip Monarch Tractors. (catalog), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Neverslip Monarch Tractors: 16-9 H. P. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Porter Tractor Company
    - The Porter Tractor: The Actual One-Man Tractor. (pamphlet), circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Titan
    - Instructions for Operating the Titan Kerosene Tractor: Two Cylinder 10-20-H. P. (pamphlet), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Twin City
    - Twin City: A tractor for every kind of work. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Velie Motors Corporation
    - Velie Biltwel Tractor: 12-24. (brochure), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wallis Tractor Co.
    - Wallis Tractor Instruction Book: Model J. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Parts Price List: Wallis Cub Junior Tractor. (catalog), circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Wisconsin Farm Tractor Sales Company
    - Wisconsin Farm Tractor: Reducing Labor and Increasing Profits on the Farm. (pamphlet), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Wisconsin Tractors. (brochure), circa 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Worthington Pump and Machinery Corporation
    - Model "A" General Service Tractor. (pamphlet), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Yuba Manufacturing Company
    - The Yuba Bulletin. (pamphlet), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series 3: Engines, 1915-1918
  - Buda Company
    - Model "YTU": Four Cylinder Unit Power Plant. (catalog, 2 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Model "HTU": Four Cylinder Unit Power Plant. (catalog), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Buffalo Pitts Company
    - Buffalo Pitts Engines. (catalog), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cushman Motor Works
    - At Last I Bring you Light Weight Power. (catalog), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - The Gasoline Engine: Its History and Principles. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Construction and Uses of the Gasoline Engine. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - International Harvester Company of America
    - Engine Operator's Guide. (pamphlet), 1916 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Manhattan Electrical Supply Co., Inc.
    - How to Run the Gas Engine-Simplified. (pamphlet), 1915 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series 4: Parts and Equipment, 1915-1922
  - American Manganese Steel Co. (AMSCO)
    - Manganese Steel Tractor Parts. (catalog), circa 1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Manganese Steel Tractor Parts. (catalog), circa 1922 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Joseph Dixon Crucible Co.
    - A Tractioneer's Guide to Good Lubrication. (pamphlet), 1919 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Foote Bros. Gear and Machine Co.
    - The Foote-Strite Transmission. (catalog), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The Foote Standard Transmission: Model D. (brochure), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The Foote Standard Transmission: Model DU and EU. (brochure), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The Foote Standard Transmission: Model FU. (brochure), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Harley-Davidson Motor Company
    - 1918 Manual: Instructions for the Setting Up, Operation, Care, and Maintenance of Harley-Davidson Motorcycles. (pamphlet), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Harley-Davidson Motorcycle Parts. (catalog), 1917 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Motor Repair Manual for the Guidance of the Motorcycle Repair Man. (pamphlet), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Edward V. Hartford, Inc.
    - Every Phase of Motoring. (catalog), circa 1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Holley Carburetor Company
    - Care and Adjustment of the Holley Model "K" Carburetor. (brochure), undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Homestead Valve Manufacturing Company
    - Homestead Valves and Other Specialties: Catalogue and Price List Showing our Complete Line of Valves, etc. (catalog), 1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hyatt Roller Bearing Co.
    - Tractor Bearings. (catalog), undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Anti-Friction Bearings on Farm Machinery. (pamphlet), circa 1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Bearing Engineering for Tractor Designers. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - International Harvester Company of America
    - Tractor Hitches. (catalog), 1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - K-W Ignition Co.
    - Instruction Book for Setting and Timing High Tension Magnetos. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Instruction Book for Setting and Timing High Tension Magnetos: 3rd Edition. (pamphlet), 1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Instruction Book for Setting and Timing High Tension Magnetos: 4th Edition. (pamphlet), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lockwood-Ash Motor Company Inc.
    - Marine Motors for Every Purse and Purpose. (catalog), circa 1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Marvel Carburetor Co.
    - Marvel's Exclusive Principle-Heat-Jacket Automatically Controlled: Improves Any Car. (catalog), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Master Carburetor Corporation
    - The Master Carburetor: The World's New Standard. (catalog), circa 1916 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mica Insulator Company
    - The Insulation of Commutators: A Few Facts Relative to an Important Subject. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Mobiloils
    - Lubrication of the Automobile: No. 2-The Chassis. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Price Maker
    - Automobile Supplies. (catalog), 1920 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rayfield Carburetors
    - Rayfield Carburetors Manual and Specification Book "C." (catalog), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Price List: Rayfield Parts. (catalog), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reflex Ignition Co.
    - Reflex Spark Plugs. (catalog), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Remy Electric Company
    - Remy: Electric Lighting, Starting, Ignition and Governor Control for Farm Tractors. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - The Story of the Electric Governor. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Remy Instruction Book: Starting, Lighting, Ignition for Tractors. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Splitdorf Electrical Co.
    - Principles of Construction and Operation of Dixie Magnetos: Instructions for their Installation, Care, and Maintenance. (pamphlet), circa 1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Standard Oil Company
    - Engine Overheating. (brochure), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correct Transmission and Rear Axle Lubrication. (brochure), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Calol Fuel Oil for Oil Injection Engines. (pamphlet), 1915 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Willard Storage Battery Co.
    - Lighting Batteries and Starting Batteries: Instructions for Charging, Care and Operation. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Who Pays? (pamphlet), 1916 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Consult in Case of Battery Trouble. (brochure), 1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Your Storage Battery: What it is and how to get the most out of it. (pamphlet), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Your Electrical System and How it Works. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Zenith Carburetor Co.
    - The Compound Nozzle Explained. (pamphlet), circa 1917 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series 5: Appliances, Electric Lighting, and Miscellaneous, 1915-1921
  - Appliances
    - How to Judge an Electric Cleaner. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Hotpoint Electric Range: 'Your Dream Come True.' (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Eureka Vacuum Cleaner Exchange. (brochure, 2 copies), circa 1915 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Simplex Ironer: "The Best Ironer." (pamphlet), 1918 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Simplex Ironer: "The Best Ironer." (catalog/letter), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - The Story of a Lump of Dirt. (pamphlet), 1919 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - ISKO Electric Refrigerator. (pamphlet), 1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Universal Electric Christmas Gifts. (brochure), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Electric Lighting
    - Be Kind to Your Eyes. Read and Write with Emeralite. (catalog), 1916 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Kohler: Automatic Power and Light 110 Volt D.C. (pamphlet), 1921 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Light Where you Want it. (catalog), circa 1920 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - How to Care for Your Electric Lighting Plant. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Instruction Book: Type "S" Inter-pole Motors. (pamphlet), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - The Way to Better Light. (catalog), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Instruction Book for Installing and Operating The Edison Storage Battery Electric Light Plant. (pamphlet), circa 1916 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Ottawa Log and Tree Saws. (pamphlet), circa 1919 (Box 2, Folder 11)